{
    "question": "1)\uf020 Manuel Marrero Cruz has been appointed the\n_______ of Cuba by the President of Cuba",
    "answer": " Prime\nMinister\n"
}{
    "question": "2)\uf020 Eight West African countries have announced the\nadoption of a new common currency named\n_______ in place of currently prevalent CFA Franc to\nend the sign of French dominance from the\nregion",
    "answer": " Eco\n"
}{
    "question": "3)\uf020 Fanni Mik\u00f3, beauty queen of ____________ won the\nMiss Intercontinental 2019",
    "answer": " Hungary\n"
}{
    "question": "4)\uf020 The International Tennis Federation has named\nWorld Champions in singles for 2019. Who won\nthe men\u2019s title",
    "answer": " Rafael Nadal of Spain\n"
}{
    "question": "5)\uf020 The women\u2019s singles title for ITF world champion\nwas won by whom",
    "answer": " Ashleigh Barty of Australia\n"
}{
    "question": "6)\uf020 Integral Coach Factory (ICF) of Indian Railways\nhas produced record 3000 Coaches in record 215\ndays. Where is this factory",
    "answer": " Chennai\n"
}{
    "question": "7)\uf020 Who has been appointed as the new Foreign\nSecretary of India",
    "answer": " Harsh Vardhan Shringla\n"
}{
    "question": "8)\uf020 Rakhi Halder created two new national records in\nweight lifting in which two categories",
    "answer": " Snatch\nand clean & Jerk\n"
}{
    "question": "9)\uf020 Who is the first Indian to win the Miss Teen\nInternational title for the first time in the 27 year\nold history of the pageant",
    "answer": " Aayushi Dholakia\n"
}{
    "question": "10)\uf020 Which country's football team has been crowned\n\"FIFA's Team of the Year\" for finishing at the top\nof the world rankings for the second year in a\nrow",
    "answer": " Belgium\n"
}{
    "question": "11)\uf020 Why December 24 has been selected to celebrate\nthe National Consumer Day in India",
    "answer": " On this day,\nthe Consumer Protection Act, 1986 had\nreceived the assent of the President\n"
}{
    "question": "12)\uf020 India celebrates National Farmers' Day (Kisan\nDiwas) to commemorate the birthday of which\nveteran farmer leader",
    "answer": " Chaudhary Charan Singh\n"
}{
    "question": "13)\uf020 Name the suave industrialist who stirred the\ncorporate world by announcing his retirement\nfrom the chairmanship of the Mahindra group\nfrom April 1, 2020",
    "answer": " Anand Mahindra\n"
}{
    "question": "14)\uf020 Devesh Srivastava has been appointed as the\nChairman and Managing Director of which public\nsector insurance company",
    "answer": " General Insurance\nCorporation of India (GIC Re)\n"
}{
    "question": "15)\uf020 International Human Solidarity Day is observed\non which day of December",
    "answer": " 20th\n"
}{
    "question": "16)\uf020 Name the new York based international credit\nrating agency that cut its growth forecast for India\nto 4.6% for the 2019-20 fiscal",
    "answer": " Fitch ratings\n"
}{
    "question": "17)\uf020 In a landmark achievement which African country\nlaunched its first satellite on Dec 20",
    "answer": " Ethiopia\n"
}{
    "question": "18)\uf020 S. Mirabai Chanu won the gold medal at the 6th\nQatar International Cup in Doha in which field",
    "answer": "\nWeight Lifting\n"
}{
    "question": "19)\uf020 Asian Development Bank approved a $490 million\nloan to upgrade about 1,600 kilometres of state\nhighways and major district roads in which state",
    "answer": "\nMadhya Pradesh\n"
}{
    "question": "20)\uf020 India successfully test-fired Pinaka missiles from\nits Integrated Test Range in Chandipur in Odisha.\nIt is what type of missile",
    "answer": " Guided Rocket System\n"
}{
    "question": "21)\uf020 DRDO successfully test fired its QR-SAM missile\nrecently. What is the full form of QR-SAM",
    "answer": " Quick\nReaction Surface-to-Air Missile\n"
}{
    "question": "22)\uf020 In a novel initiative, which Municipal Corporation\nrecently launched India\u2019s first online waste\nexchange platform and app",
    "answer": " Chennai\n"
}{
    "question": "23)\uf020 With which country India conducted a 2+2\ndialogue on Dec 18",
    "answer": " USA\n"
}{
    "question": "24)\uf020 The 2nd Indo-US ministerial 2+2 dialogue was\nheld in which city",
    "answer": " US capitol Washington DC\n"
}{
    "question": "25)\uf020 Which two ministers from each country\nparticipated in the Indo-US ministerial 2+2\ndialogue",
    "answer": " Defence Minister and Foreign\nMinister\n"
}{
    "question": "26)\uf020 Which 3 tech giants have joined hands to develop\na framework titled \u2018Connected Home over IP\u2019 for\nbetter compatibility among their smart home\nproducts",
    "answer": " Amazon, Apple and Google\n"
}{
    "question": "27)\uf020 What is the name of the smart voice based\nservices developed by the Amazon, Apple and\nGoogle",
    "answer": " Amazon Alexa, Apple Siri and Google\nAssistant\n"
}{
    "question": "28)\uf020 _______ has become the 3rd Indian firm and the\nfirst Indian bank to cross $100 billion mark in\nmarket capitalization",
    "answer": " HDFC Bank\n"
}{
    "question": "29)\uf020 How do we calculate market capitalization value\nof a company",
    "answer": " No. of Shares x Market price of\nshare\n"
}{
    "question": "30)\uf020 Name the Prime Minister of Portugal who came to\nIndia on a two day, Dec 19-20 visit",
    "answer": " Antonio\nCosta\nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 78\n"
}{
    "question": "31)\uf020 Which country announced the launching of a\n\u201cGandhi Citizenship Education Prize\u201d in the\nhonour of Gandhian values",
    "answer": " Portugal\n"
}{
    "question": "32)\uf020 ________ is the capital of Portugal",
    "answer": " Lisbon\n"
}{
    "question": "33)\uf020 Name the celebrity who secured the first position\nin the Forbes India\u2019s Celebrity-100 list",
    "answer": " Virat\nKohli\n"
}{
    "question": "34)\uf020 Mind Master is the title of the autobiography of\nwhich legendary chess player",
    "answer": " Viswanathan\nAnand\n"
}{
    "question": "35)\uf020 \"Phir Meri Yaad\" is a popular book written by\nwhich author",
    "answer": " Dr. Kumar Vishwas\n"
}{
    "question": "36)\uf020 Who is the author of the famous novel \"Raavan",
    "answer": "\nEnemy of Aryavarta\"? Amish Tripathi\n"
}{
    "question": "37)\uf020 Recently, there was a headline in the business\nsection of the newspaper \"PSA group and Fiat\nannounce merger\". The news relates to which\nindustry",
    "answer": " Automobiles\n"
}{
    "question": "38)\uf020 India successfully conducted trials of two variants\nof supersonic cruise missile BrahMos. The air\nforce variant was fired from which fighter jet",
    "answer": " SU30MKI Sukhoi\n"
}{
    "question": "39)\uf020 Which state Police was honoured with\n\u2018President\u2019s Colours\u2019 for their outstanding\nservices, the highest honour given to a police\nforce in India",
    "answer": " Gujarat\n"
}{
    "question": "40)\uf020 State Bank of India signed a loan agreement for\n$277 million (about Rs 1,958 crore) with\ndevelopment bank of which country",
    "answer": " Germany\n"
}{
    "question": "41)\uf020 Name the England cricketer who has been voted\n\u201cBBC Sports Personality of the Year-2019\u201d",
    "answer": " Ben\nStokes\n"
}{
    "question": "42)\uf020 One of the oldest and most esteemed classical\nmusic festivals in India, the \u2018Tansen Samaroh\u2019 was\nheld in which place",
    "answer": " Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh\n"
}{
    "question": "43)\uf020 The Union government launched National\nBroadband Mission to provide Broadband access\nto all ________ by 2022",
    "answer": " Villages\n"
}{
    "question": "44)\uf020 What is the theme of this year's International\nMigrants Day observed on December 18",
    "answer": " #We\ntogether\n"
}{
    "question": "45)\uf020 In a landmark ruling, the National Company Law\nAppellate Tribunal (NCLAT) reinstated_____as the\nexecutive chairman of the Tata Sons on December\n18, 2019",
    "answer": " Cyrus Mistry\n"
}{
    "question": "46)\uf020 Name the veteran Hindi and Marathi theatre and\nfilm actor, an ENT surgeon by profession, who\nwas passed away recently",
    "answer": " Dr. Shriram Lagoo\n"
}{
    "question": "47)\uf020 Which Indian paramilitary force has started a\ndedicated matrimonial site for its staff",
    "answer": " IndoTibetan Border Police (ITBP)\n"
}{
    "question": "48)\uf020 The recently released Gender Gap Index-2019 by\nthe World Economic Forum, what is the rank of\nIndia",
    "answer": " 112th\n"
}{
    "question": "49)\uf020 Which country has been ranked as the most\nappropriate country for women representation in\nthe Gender Gap Index-2019",
    "answer": " Iceland\n"
}{
    "question": "50)\uf020 RBI has asked the banks to waive off service\ncharge on online usage of which of its remittance\nfacility",
    "answer": " NEFT\n"
}{
    "question": "51)\uf020 The free NEFT service will be available from\nwhich date",
    "answer": " January 01, 2020\n"
}{
    "question": "52)\uf020 The free NEFT service will be available to which\ncategory of customers",
    "answer": " Savings Bank Account\nHolders\n"
}{
    "question": "53)\uf020 DSC Prize for South Asian Literature 2019 was\nwon by which author",
    "answer": " Amitabha Bagchi\n"
}{
    "question": "54)\uf020 Amitabha Bagchi won the DSC Prize for South\nAsian Literature 2019 for which novel",
    "answer": " Half The\nNight Is Gone\n"
}{
    "question": "55)\uf020 Which corporate emerged at number one spot in\nterms of revenue generated in 2018-19, ending\nthe state-owned Indian Oil Corporation's 10-year\nreign as India\u2019s largest company",
    "answer": " Reliance\nIndustries Ltd.\n"
}{
    "question": "56)\uf020 Kento Momota, world no. 1 won his 11th\nbadminton title of the year at the BWF World\nTour Finals. He is from which country",
    "answer": " Japan\n"
}{
    "question": "57)\uf020 Who is the world's new number one women's\nbadminton champion",
    "answer": " Chen Yufei\n"
}{
    "question": "58)\uf020 Chen Yufei hails from which country",
    "answer": " China\n"
}{
    "question": "59)\uf020 The Supreme Court ruled that states which have\ndistricts where more than _____ cases of child\nabuse under POCSO Act should establish at least 2\nspecial courts in each such district",
    "answer": " 300\n"
}{
    "question": "60)\uf020 A conference of 46 Heads of Central Universities\nand Institutes of Higher Learning was held at\nwhich place in New Delhi",
    "answer": " Rashtrapti Bhawan\n"
}{
    "question": "61)\uf020 Which country recently elected its former Prime\nMinister, Abdelmadjid Tebboune as its new\nPresident",
    "answer": " Algeria\n"
}{
    "question": "62)\uf020 Who has been appointed as the next chief of the\nIndian Army in the rank of General",
    "answer": " Lt Gen\nManoj Mukund Naravane\n"
}{
    "question": "63)\uf020 Miss Toni-Ann Singh bagged which beauty crown\nat a ceremony held in London",
    "answer": " Miss World 2019\n"
}{
    "question": "64)\uf020 Lakshya Sen notched up his fifth title of the\nseason, claiming the men\u2019s singles crown at the\nBangladesh International Challenger Cup in which\nsports",
    "answer": " Badminton\n"
}{
    "question": "65)\uf020 Rohit Sharma, noted cricketer has been appointed\nas the brand ambassador of the which top Spanish\nFootball Club",
    "answer": " La Liga\n"
}{
    "question": "66)\uf020 Noted Hindi author and Sahitya Akademi awardee\n71 year old Nasera Sharma recently won which\ntop literary award",
    "answer": " Vyas Samman\n"
}{
    "question": "67)\uf020 Nasera Sharma won the Vyas Samman for which\nnovel",
    "answer": " Kaagaz Ki Naav\n"
}{
    "question": "68)\uf020 India celebrates Vijay Diwas on December 16 to\ncommemorate its victory in which war",
    "answer": " 1971\nPakistan War \nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 79\n"
}{
    "question": "69)\uf020 Who was the hero of the 1971 Pakistan war, who\nmanaged surrender of about 93,000 Pakistani\nsoldiers",
    "answer": " Lt Gen Jagjit Singh Arora\n"
}{
    "question": "70)\uf020 Which day is organized by the Energy Efficiency\nBureau on Dec 14 to showcase India's\nachievements in energy efficiency and\nconservation",
    "answer": " National Energy Conservation\nDay\n"
}{
    "question": "71)\uf020 Name the Indian politician who has been ranked\n34th in the Forbes' 100 Most Powerful Women\nList - 2019",
    "answer": " Nirmala Sitharaman\n"
}{
    "question": "72)\uf020 What is the position of Ms. Nirmala Sitharaman in\nthe Indian political system",
    "answer": " Finance Minister\n"
}{
    "question": "73)\uf020 Name the British political leader who led his party\nto victory in the recent General elections held on\nDecember 13",
    "answer": " Boris Johnson\n"
}{
    "question": "74)\uf020 G S Lakshmi, noted Indian woman match referee\nand former all rounder from Andhra Pradesh was\nin news recently for which achievement",
    "answer": " She has\nbeen selected by the ICC to become the first\nwoman match referee in the world to officiate\na men\u2019s ODI match\n"
}{
    "question": "75)\uf020 Which apex national organization has identified\n138 numbers of monuments as \u201cMust-See\nMonuments\u201d",
    "answer": " Archaeological Survey of India\n"
}{
    "question": "76)\uf020 The Citizenship Amendment Bill, 2019 (CAB)\npassed by the Parliament on Dec 11 aims to grant\nIndian citizenship to people of which 6 religions",
    "answer": "\nHindu, Christian, Sikh, Parsi, Jain, and\nBuddhist\n"
}{
    "question": "77)\uf020 The Citizenship Amendment Bill, 2019 aims to\ngrant Indian citizenship to Hindu, Christian, Sikh,\nParsi, Jain, and Buddhist people who have fled\nfrom which 3 countries",
    "answer": " Pakistan, Afghanistan\nand Bangladesh\n"
}{
    "question": "78)\uf020 The Asian Development Bank (ADB) has sharply\nscaled down its projection for India's economic\ngrowth to ______ in 2019-20 from 6.5% projected\nearlier",
    "answer": " 5.1%\n"
}{
    "question": "79)\uf020 Name the veteran opener from Maharashtra who\nbecame the first player in India cricket to feature\nin 150 Ranji matches",
    "answer": " Wasim Jaffer\n"
}{
    "question": "80)\uf020 Name the 14 year old Grandmaster from Chennai\nwho won the FIDE Open category of the London\nChess Classic held in London",
    "answer": " R.\nPraggnanandhaa\n"
}{
    "question": "81)\uf020 Who has been selected as 'Person of the Year' for\nthe year 2019 by the Time magazine",
    "answer": " Greta\nThunberg\n"
}{
    "question": "82)\uf020 The National Anti Doping Agency (NADA) has\nselected which Bollywood celebrity as its bran\nambassador",
    "answer": " Suniel Shetty\n"
}{
    "question": "83)\uf020 The Lok Sabha on Dec 11 passed the Constitution\n(126th) Amendment Bill. It is related to which\nissue",
    "answer": " Extending the reservation quota for SCs\nand STs in the Lok Sabha and the state assemblies by another 10 years\n"
}{
    "question": "84)\uf020 The Constitution (126th) Amendment Bill aims to\nextend the reservation quota for SCs and STs in\nthe Lok Sabha and the state assemblies by\nanother 10 years, till what date",
    "answer": " January 25,\n2030\n"
}{
    "question": "85)\uf020 ISRO launched earth observation satellite named\n_________ along with nine foreign satellites aboard\nPSLV-C48",
    "answer": " RISAT-2BR1\n"
}{
    "question": "86)\uf020 India entered the top ten countries group in this\nyear's Climate Change Performance Index (CCPI)\nat which rank",
    "answer": " 9th\n"
}{
    "question": "87)\uf020 This year's Climate Change Performance Index is\ntopped by which country",
    "answer": " Sweden\n"
}{
    "question": "88)\uf020 Which international day is observed on December\n11 with support from UNO to encourage\nsustainable development in mountains all over\nthe world",
    "answer": " International Mountain Day\n"
}{
    "question": "89)\uf020 Which country hosted the 13th South Asian\nGames from Dec 1 to 10",
    "answer": " Nepal\n"
}{
    "question": "90)\uf020 Which country topped the medal tally at the 13th\nSouth Asian Games",
    "answer": " India\n"
}{
    "question": "91)\uf020 Which city of United Arab Emirates-UAE has been\nselected as the world\u2019s leading sports tourism\ndestination",
    "answer": " Abu Dhabi\n"
}{
    "question": "92)\uf020 Export-Import Bank of India (Exim Bank)\nprovided $500 million (Rs 3561 crore) Line of\nCredit to which country for funding the defencerelated procurement",
    "answer": " Bangladesh\n"
}{
    "question": "93)\uf020 Headquarters of the EXIM Bank are located in\nwhich Indian city",
    "answer": " Mumbai\n"
}{
    "question": "94)\uf020 Which US retail major has announced that it will\ntrain 50,000 entrepreneurs from the micro, small\n& medium enterprises (MSME) sector in India",
    "answer": "\nWalmart\n"
}{
    "question": "95)\uf020 George J. Laurer, the engineer whose invention\ntransformed handling of products in retail and\nother industries around the world, died at the age\nof 94. What was his invention",
    "answer": " Bar Code\n"
}{
    "question": "96)\uf020 A volcano suddenly erupted on Dec 9 on White\nIsland claiming over 18 lives. Where is this island",
    "answer": "\nOff the north coast of New Zealand's North\nIsland\n"
}{
    "question": "97)\uf020 India's ranking in the Human Development Index\n2019 improved marginally by ______ rank to 129\nthis year",
    "answer": " One\n"
}{
    "question": "98)\uf020 The Human Development Index is associated with\nwhich UN agency",
    "answer": " UNDP- United Nations\nDevelopment Programme\n"
}{
    "question": "99)\uf020 The Human Development Index-2019 is topped\nby which country",
    "answer": " Norway\n"
}{
    "question": "100)\uf020 The World Anti-Doping Agency, WADA, banned\nwhich country for four years, from participation\nin global sporting events",
    "answer": " Russia\n"
}{
    "question": "101)\uf020 The headquarters of WADA are located in which\ncity",
    "answer": " Montreal\nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 80\n"
}{
    "question": "102)\uf020 The Paika rebellion, a 200-year-old armed revolt\nin 1817 against the British East India Company\ntook place in which state",
    "answer": " Odisha\n"
}{
    "question": "103)\uf020 The UNO promotes the celebration of Human\nRights Day on which date of December",
    "answer": " 10\n"
}{
    "question": "104)\uf020 The Indian Navy celebrates National Submarine\nDay on Dec 09 to commemorate the induction of\nthe first submarine. What was its name",
    "answer": " INS\nKalvari\n"
}{
    "question": "105)\uf020 Who is Britain\u2019s top boxer who reclaimed his\nworld heavyweight crown from Andy Ruiz of\nAmerica",
    "answer": " Anthony Joshua\n"
}{
    "question": "106)\uf020 Which country elected Sanna Marin as the\nyoungest (34) Prime Minister of the world",
    "answer": "\nFinland\n"
}{
    "question": "107)\uf020 The Miss Earth 2019 crown was won by Nellys\nPimentel. She hails from which country",
    "answer": " Puerto\nRico\n"
}{
    "question": "108)\uf020 Miss Zozibini Tunzi, a black beauty from South\nAfrica created waves by winning the __________\ncrown at Atlanta USA",
    "answer": " Miss Universe 2019\n"
}{
    "question": "109)\uf020 As per the recent RBI guidelines, the NEFT facility\nfor online transfer of funds, shall now be available\nfrom _______ to _________ time",
    "answer": " 24x7 (All time, all\ndays)\n"
}{
    "question": "110)\uf020 As per the recent RBI guidelines, the NEFT facility\nwill now have how many settlement batches",
    "answer": " 48\n"
}{
    "question": "111)\uf020 Aberdeen Police station has been declared as the\nbest police station of the country by the Home\nMinistry. It is at which place",
    "answer": " Andaman Nicobar\nIslands\n"
}{
    "question": "112)\uf020 A total 799 Van Dhan Vikas Kendra in the 24\nstates have been opened till date, for the benefit\nof which community",
    "answer": " Forest Tribals\n"
}{
    "question": "113)\uf020 The fitness and wellness application by which\nactress was awarded Google Play's Best App of\n2019 in the ''Personal Growth'' category",
    "answer": " Shilpa\nShetty\n"
}{
    "question": "114)\uf020 The two day summit of world\u2019s most powerful\ndefence alliance, NATO-(North Atlantic Treaty\nOrganization) was held in which city",
    "answer": " London\n"
}{
    "question": "115)\uf020 Headquarters of NATO are located in which city",
    "answer": "\nBrussels, Belgium\n"
}{
    "question": "116)\uf020 Name the legendary Swiss tennis player who\nbecame the first living person in Switzerland to\nhave a coin minted in his honour",
    "answer": " Roger Federer\n"
}{
    "question": "117)\uf020 The RBI recently released guidelines for \u2018on tap\u2019\nlicensing of which type of banks in the private\nsector",
    "answer": " Small Finance Bank\n"
}{
    "question": "118)\uf020 What is the minimum capital requirement for\nsetting up a Small Finance Bank",
    "answer": " Rs. 200 crore\n"
}{
    "question": "119)\uf020 What is the name of the world's largest oil\ncompany, owned by the Saudi Arabia",
    "answer": " Saudi\nAramco\n"
}{
    "question": "120)\uf020 The Saudi Aramco was in news in the first week of\nDecember, 2019 for what reasons",
    "answer": " It came out\nwith world's largest IPO for $25.6 billion\n"
}{
    "question": "121)\uf020 What is the name of the joint military exercise of\nIndia and Russia held from 10 to 19 December",
    "answer": "\nIndra\n"
}{
    "question": "122)\uf020 Indra - the joint military exercise of India and\nRussia was hosted by which country",
    "answer": " India\n"
}{
    "question": "123)\uf020 Which national day is observed on Dec. 07 to\nexpress gratitude to the martyrs who sacrifice\ntheir lives for safeguarding the country\u2019s honour",
    "answer": "\nArmed Forces Flag Day\n"
}{
    "question": "124)\uf020 Name the Chess Grandmaster from Chennai who\nbecame the youngest Indian to cross the Elo\nrating of 2,600",
    "answer": " R Praggnanandhaa\n"
}{
    "question": "125)\uf020 Which Indian celebrity was awarded the Danny\nKaye Humanitarian Award from UNICEF for\nsupporting the cause of UNICEF for the last 15\nyears",
    "answer": " Priyanka Chopra\n"
}{
    "question": "126)\uf020 Name the railway station that became the first\nstation to get the \u2018Eat Right Station\u2019 certification\nwith four stars rating by the FSSAI",
    "answer": " Mumbai\nCentral\n"
}{
    "question": "127)\uf020 What is the name of the 8th Indo-China joint\ntraining military exercise held at Umroi,\nMeghalaya from 07 to 20 December",
    "answer": " Hand in\nHand 2019\n"
}{
    "question": "128)\uf020 All the Members of Parliament (MPs)\nunanimously decided to give up the subsidy on\nwhich item",
    "answer": " Food in canteen of Parliament\n"
}{
    "question": "129)\uf020 The World Soil Day is observed annually on\nDecember 5 with support from which UN agency",
    "answer": "\nFAO - Food and Agriculture Organization\n"
}{
    "question": "130)\uf020 Which country passed The Hong Kong Human\nRights and Democracy Act of 2019 in November\nend, supporting the pro-democracy protesters in\nHong Kong",
    "answer": " United States of America\n"
}{
    "question": "131)\uf020 USA passed the Uighur Human Rights Policy Act,\nwhich calls for an end to the detention, torture\nand harassment of over a million Uighurs and\nother Muslim ethnic minorities in which country",
    "answer": "\nChina\n"
}{
    "question": "132)\uf020 Masatsugu Asakawa, has been elected as the new\nPresident of which global financial agency",
    "answer": " Asian\nDevelopment Bank\n"
}{
    "question": "133)\uf020 The Headquarters of the Asian Development Bank\nare situated in _______, Philippines",
    "answer": " Manila\n"
}{
    "question": "134)\uf020 How many countries are the members of the\nAsian Development Bank",
    "answer": " 69\n"
}{
    "question": "135)\uf020 Masatsugu Asakawa is the former Minister of\nFinance of which country",
    "answer": " Japan\n"
}{
    "question": "136)\uf020 Which day is observed every year on Dec 05 to\nshow gratitude towards all those people who are\nworking free of charge and help other people\nwithout monetary benefits",
    "answer": " International\nVolunteer Day\n"
}{
    "question": "137)\uf020 According to the Global Climate Risk Index 2020,\nIndia is the _________ most climate-affected country \nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 81\nin 2018",
    "answer": " 5th\n"
}{
    "question": "138)\uf020 The Union Government launched the 4th round of\nthe regional connectivity scheme \u201cUDAN 4.0\".\nWhat is the focus area of this version",
    "answer": " Jammu\nand Kashmir, Ladakh, Northeast, hilly states\nand islands\n"
}{
    "question": "139)\uf020 The Lok Sabha passed the Recycling of Ships Bill,\n2019 on Dec 3. Where in India we have the largest\nship breaking centre",
    "answer": " Alang, Gujarat\n"
}{
    "question": "140)\uf020 Which global rating agency has reaffirmed India\u2019s\nsovereign credit rating at BBB with stable\noutlook",
    "answer": " S&P (Standard & Poor\u2019s)\n"
}{
    "question": "141)\uf020 The government plans to set up a specialised\nrecruitment agency for conducting a single\nexam\u2014 Common Eligibility Test (CET)\u2014for\nrecruiting employees in which cadre",
    "answer": " Group B\nand C\n"
}{
    "question": "142)\uf020 The Alphabet company, owner of Google, named\nwhom as the next CEO of the company",
    "answer": " Sundar\nPichai\n"
}{
    "question": "143)\uf020 The Asian Development Bank approved 206\nmillion dollar loan to develop water supply and\nsewerage infrastructure in 5 cities of which\nIndian state",
    "answer": " Tamil Nadu\n"
}{
    "question": "144)\uf020 The country's first National Maritime Heritage\nMuseum is being setup at________, a site of\nHarappan era on the Saurashtra coast in Gujarat",
    "answer": "\nLothal\n"
}{
    "question": "145)\uf020 The maritime museum at Lothal is being setup\nwith technical support from the Maritime\nHeritage Museum of which country",
    "answer": " Portugal\n"
}{
    "question": "146)\uf020 What was the name of the joint military exercise\nheld in Salijhandi, Nepal between India and Nepal\nfrom Dec 3 to 16",
    "answer": " Surya Kiran\n"
}{
    "question": "147)\uf020 Which star football player won the Ballon d'Or\n2019 (Golden Ball) for the record 6th time",
    "answer": "\nLionel Messi\n"
}{
    "question": "148)\uf020 Lionel Messi hails from which country and plays\nfor which football club",
    "answer": " Argentina, Barcelona\n"
}{
    "question": "149)\uf020 Who won the Ballon d'Or 2019 (Golden Ball) for\nwomen",
    "answer": " Megan Rapinoe\n"
}{
    "question": "150)\uf020 Megan Rapinoe is the star footballer of which\ncountry",
    "answer": " USA\n"
}{
    "question": "151)\uf020 Which day is celebrated in honour of the maritime\nforce's role during the 1971 Pakistan war?\nDecember 04",
    "answer": " Indian Navy Day\n"
}{
    "question": "152)\uf020 Which National Day is observed to pay homage to\nthe thousands of victims of the Bhopal gas\ntragedy and create awareness about the need for\npollution control? December 02",
    "answer": " National\nPollution Control Day\n"
}{
    "question": "153)\uf020 Sri Lanka\u2019s newly elected President________ ,\narrived in New Delhi on his maiden state visit\nabroad, from Nov 28 to 30",
    "answer": " Gotabaya Rajapaksa\n"
}{
    "question": "154)\uf020 What is the currency of Sri Lanka",
    "answer": " Sri Lankan\nRupee\n"
}{
    "question": "155)\uf020 Which company became the first financial sector\nplayer to file for bankruptcy proceedings before\nthe Mumbai bench of the National Company Law\nTribunal",
    "answer": " DHFL (Dewan Housing Finance\nCorporation Ltd)\n"
}{
    "question": "156)\uf020 Which Indian film crossed the Rs 2,000-crore\nmark at the global box-office to become the\nbiggest blockbuster of the decade",
    "answer": " Dangal\n"
}{
    "question": "157)\uf020 The government has decided to make hallmarking\nof which jewellery and artefacts compulsory from\nJanuary 15, 2021",
    "answer": " Gold\n"
}{
    "question": "158)\uf020 Which Indian organization is authorised to carry\nout the hallmarking of gold jewellery",
    "answer": " BISBureau of Indian Standards\n"
}{
    "question": "159)\uf020 The 7th edition of India-Sri Lanka joint army\nexercise was held at Aundh Military Station, Pune.\nWhat was its name",
    "answer": " Mitra Shakti\n"
}{
    "question": "160)\uf020 In a hallmarked gold ornament, how many\nsymbols or signs are to be checked",
    "answer": " Four\n"
}{
    "question": "161)\uf020 Tejinder Pal Singh Toor was India\u2019s flag-bearer at\nthe South Asian Games opening ceremony. He\nplays which event in athletics",
    "answer": " Shot Put\n"
}{
    "question": "162)\uf020 Which country became the first Arab nation to\ntake over the G20 presidency from Japan",
    "answer": " Saudi\nArabia\n"
}{
    "question": "163)\uf020 What is the name of the longest train (in terms of\ndistance covered) of India",
    "answer": " Vivek Express\n"
}{
    "question": "164)\uf020 The Vivek Express runs between __________, Assam\nto Kanyakumari, Tamil Nadu",
    "answer": " Dibrugarh\n"
}{
    "question": "165)\uf020 Who has been selected to lead India's cricket\nteam in the next year's Under-19 ICC Cricket\nWorld Cup to be held in South Africa",
    "answer": " Priyam\nGarg\n"
}{
    "question": "166)\uf020 Senior Wrestling National Championship was\nheld in ___________ from Nov 29 to Dec 01",
    "answer": "\nJalandhar\n"
}{
    "question": "167)\uf020 Which state you will have to visit to take part in\nHornbill Festival",
    "answer": " Nagaland\n"
}{
    "question": "168)\uf020 The 25th Conference of Parties (COP25) to UN\nClimate Change Conference was held from Dec 2\nto 13 in which city",
    "answer": " Madrid, Spain\n"
}{
    "question": "169)\uf020 The 25th Conference of Parties (COP25) to UN\nClimate Change Conference was held to give\nfinishing touches to which climate accord",
    "answer": " 2015\nParis climate change accord\n"
}{
    "question": "170)\uf020 World AIDS Day is observed on December 01.\nWhat is the full form of AIDS",
    "answer": " Acquired Immuno\nDeficiency Syndrome\n"
}{
    "question": "171)\uf020 AIDS is a pandemic disease caused due to the\ninfection of HIV. What is the full form of HIV",
    "answer": "\nHuman Immunodeficiency Virus\n"
}{
    "question": "172)\uf020 What is the theme of this year's World Aids Day",
    "answer": "\nCommunities Make the Difference\n"
}{
    "question": "173)\uf020 King and Queen of which country arrived on a 5\nday state visit to India, from Dec. 2 to 6",
    "answer": " Sweden\n"
}{
    "question": "174)\uf020 Which city is the capital of Sweden",
    "answer": " Stockholm \nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 82\n"
}{
    "question": "175)\uf020 Govt. launched \u201cIntensified Mission Indradhanush\n2.0\u201d across India on December 2. It is associated\nwith which issue",
    "answer": " Immunization\n"
}{
    "question": "176)\uf020 Intensified Mission Indradhanush 2.0 covers\npreventive vaccine for how many diseases",
    "answer": " Eight\n"
}{
    "question": "177)\uf020 International Day for the Abolition of Slavery,\nobserved on December 02 is supported by which\nUN agency",
    "answer": " International Labour Organisation\n(ILO)\n"
}{
    "question": "178)\uf020 The Etawah Lion Safari, one of the biggest safari\nparks in Asia, is located in which Indian state",
    "answer": "\nUttar Pradesh\n"
}{
    "question": "179)\uf020 Which city in Odisha hosted the National Tribal\nCraft Mela\u20132019 from Nov 23 to 29",
    "answer": "\nBhubaneswar\n"
}{
    "question": "180)\uf020 Which state has decided to set up the state\u2019s first\nvulture conservation and breeding centre in\nFarenda area",
    "answer": " Uttar Pradesh\n"
}{
    "question": "181)\uf020 ________ became the first Indian company to cross\nRs.10 trillion mark in market capitalization",
    "answer": "\nReliance Industries Ltd\n"
}{
    "question": "182)\uf020 Which state has decided to declare Guru Ghasidas\nNational Park in Korea district as the fourth tiger\nreserve of the state",
    "answer": " Chhattisgarh\n"
}{
    "question": "183)\uf020 Name the former deputy governor of RBI who has\nbeen appointed as the first chairman of the\nsteering committee of the Code for Responsible\nLending (CRL) in micro-credit",
    "answer": " H R Khan\n"
}{
    "question": "184)\uf020 ____________ has become the first country in the\nworld to completely digitize the Hajj process",
    "answer": "\nIndia\n"
}{
    "question": "185)\uf020 The Muslims visit which holy place to complete\ntheir Hajj pilgrimage",
    "answer": " Mecca\n"
}{
    "question": "186)\uf020 What is the popular name of the holiest shrine of\nMuslims located in Mecca",
    "answer": " Kaaba or Quaba\n"
}{
    "question": "187)\uf020 Which Indian General is being tipped to become\nIndia\u2019s first Chief of Defence Staff \u2013 a four-star\nposition being created as part of a defence\nmanagement overhaul",
    "answer": " General Bipin Rawat\n"
}{
    "question": "188)\uf020 G Satheesh Reddy, Chairman DRDO, has been\nselected for the Honorary Fellowship of which\nprestigious society",
    "answer": " Royal Aeronautical Society,\nLondon\n"
}{
    "question": "189)\uf020 Navies of India and __________ conducted their first\nbilateral exercise \u201cMine Countermeasure\nExercise (MINEX) 2019\u201d",
    "answer": " Japan\n"
}{
    "question": "190)\uf020 \u201cMine Countermeasure Exercise (MINEX) 2019\u201d\nwas conducted at which place",
    "answer": " Kochi, Kerala\n"
}{
    "question": "191)\uf020 The 47th All India Police Science Congress\n(AIPSC) was hosted by the capital of which state",
    "answer": "\nUttar Pradesh\n"
}{
    "question": "192)\uf020 Abhishek Verma and Jyothi Surekha Vennam\nclaimed the gold in compound mixed pair event of\nwhich sport in Bangkok, Thailand",
    "answer": " Archery\n"
}{
    "question": "193)\uf020 Which apex national institution has adopted a\nnew motto, \u201cMa Gridhah Kasyasvidhanam (Do not\nbe greedy for anyone\u2019s wealth)\u201d",
    "answer": " The Lokpal of\nIndia\n"
}{
    "question": "194)\uf020 Name the renowned cartoonist whose works\ngraced several newspapers in a career spanning\n58 years, who passed away in Noida, UP",
    "answer": " Sudhir\nDar\n"
}{
    "question": "195)\uf020 FIH-International Hockey Federation has\napproved India\u2019s bid to host the Men\u2019s Hockey\nWorld Cup 2023 in which state",
    "answer": " Odisha\n"
}{
    "question": "196)\uf020 Name the Indian who is current President of FIHInternational Hockey Federation",
    "answer": " Narinder Batra\n"
}{
    "question": "197)\uf020 The Union Ministry of Shipping has approved the\ndevelopment of the Loktak Inland Waterways\nProject in which state",
    "answer": " Manipur\n"
}{
    "question": "198)\uf020 What is the special feature of the Loktak Lake",
    "answer": " It\nis the biggest fresh water lake in North East\n"
}{
    "question": "199)\uf020 Which prestigious prize for literature has been\nannounced for the eminent poet Akkitham\nAchuthan Namboodri",
    "answer": " Jnanpith Award\n"
}{
    "question": "200)\uf020 Eminent poet Akkitham is associated with which\nlanguage",
    "answer": " Malayalam\n"
}{
    "question": "201)\uf020 The Jnanpith award, regarded as one of the\nhighest literary award, carries cash award of what\namount",
    "answer": " Rs. 11 lakh\n"
}{
    "question": "202)\uf020 The Jnanpith award can be given to outstanding\nliterary work of any one of the ___ languages\nrecognized in the Indian constitution",
    "answer": " 22\n"
}{
    "question": "203)\uf020 The Indian Army successfully test-fired two Spike\nLR Missiles recently. These are what type of\nmissile",
    "answer": " Anti Tank Missile\n"
}{
    "question": "204)\uf020 Which film won the Golden Peacock award for the\nbest film at the recently concluded International\nFilm Festival of India",
    "answer": " Particles\n"
}{
    "question": "205)\uf020 Who is the director of the film 'Particles'",
    "answer": " Blaisse\nHarrison, France\n"
}{
    "question": "206)\uf020 The Best Director award at the recently\nconcluded IFFI was won by whom",
    "answer": " Lijo Jose\nPellissery for his Malayalam film \u201cJallikattu\u201d\n"
}{
    "question": "207)\uf020 What is the amount of cash amount given with the\nGolden Peacock",
    "answer": " Rs. 40 lakh\n"
}{
    "question": "208)\uf020 The Lok Sabha approved a bill on November 27\nfor the merger of two union territories into one.\nName these union territories",
    "answer": " Dadra & Nagar\nHaveli and Daman & Diu\n"
}{
    "question": "209)\uf020 After the merger of Dadra and Nagar Haveli and\nDaman and Diu, how many UTs are there now in\nIndia",
    "answer": " 8\n"
}{
    "question": "210)\uf020 HRD Ministry launched the kartavya.ugc.ac.in\nportal as a part of year long \u201cNagrik Kartavya\nPaalan Abhiyan\u201d being observed throughout the\ncountry. It is related to which feature of the\nIndian constitution",
    "answer": " Fundamental Duties\n"
}{
    "question": "211)\uf020 The fundamental duties are mentioned in which\narticle of the constitution",
    "answer": " 51A\n"
}{
    "question": "212)\uf020 How many fundamental duties are mentioned in\nthe Article 51A of the Constitution",
    "answer": " 11\nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 83\n"
}{
    "question": "213)\uf020 The ISRO on Nov 27 launched advanced earth\nimaging and mapping satellite. What is its name",
    "answer": "\nCARTOSAT-3\nNOVEMBER 2019\n"
}